Guide to the Henry Walter Papers 1950-2017 MS 3016
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Public Relations Files. Abraham D. Beame, 1961-2000s (bulk, 1969-1977); 22.92 Linear feet
  - Subseries I.A. Comptrollership Years, 1961-1974 (bulk, 1969-1973); 8.75 Linear feet
    - Compendium of Beame's Campaign Proposals, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15)
      Includes a compendium prepared by the campaign's Research Department, circa November 1973, and a version of Beame's mayoral inaugural address.
    - Women's City Club Address / Commission on Status of Women, 1973 October (Offsite-box 8, Folder 16)
    - Housing in the Non-Urban Setting: An Initial Report on Problems and Programs, 1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 17)
      Includes a paper sent to HUD by the West Virginia Housing Development Fund. The paper was forwarded to Walter by one of its co-authors, with a letter proposing national growth policy as a possible campaign theme for Beame.
    - Time Records, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 18)
      Includes Walter's summary of his daily hours worked from mid-1971 to the end of 1972.
    - Miscellaneous, Circa 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 19)
      Includes two portrait photographs, one of Beame and one of him with his wife; a parody letter from the Committee to Erect a Statue of John V. Lindsay; list of Comptroller's Office staff; draft of a letter from Beame to Robert Moses concerning Moses's proposal for Beame to be a member of the Metropolitan Museum of Art's committee on purchases and sales of art objects; clippings; and other items.
    - Annual Report of the Comptroller of the City of New York for Fiscal Year 1970-1971, 1971 October 31 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 20)
    - First Mayoralty Campaign, 1961, 1965 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1)
      Includes a transcript of NBC's Meet the Press broadcast of October 17, 1965, which included mayoral candidates Beame, William F. Buckley, Jr. and John V. Lindsay; William F. Buckley Jr's announcement as mayoral candidate; Buckley's biography; and a New York Times Magazine article. Also an unrelated 1961 press release from Mayor Wagner's office.
    - Presentation of the Reception Wing of Gracie Mansion, 1966 September 27 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 2)
      Includes the booklet prepared by the Committee for Gracie Mansion, Inc. on the occasion of the presentation of the Reception Wing to the city.
    - "Crisis in New York City's Finances: Causes and Cures", 1968 January 4 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3)
      Includes the text of then-former Comptroller Beame's remarks at the Citizens Union and New School for Social Research.
    - Revenue Reform Proposals, 1969-1972 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 4)
      Includes correspondence and other documents concerning Comptroller candidate Beame's revenue proposals, especially for a joint state-city fiscal commission (1969, 1971); includes a letter from Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller (1969). Also includes correspondence with Mayor John V. Lindsay concerning a proposed executive branch reorganization, particularly with regard to "superagencies" (January 1970); letter to President Richard Nixon supporting a tax incentive program for employee training (January 1970); and an outline of remarks for the Midtown Council (October 5, 1972).
    - Tax Reform (4 folders), 1969 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 5-8)
      Includes correspondence, analyses, statements, and other documents concerning Comptroller candidate Beame's various tax/revenue reform proposals, including those related to off-track betting (OTB), tax sharing, real estate tax exemptions, and others.
    - Clippings. 1970 September-December (Offsite-box 8, Folder 21)
    - Clippings. 1971 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 22-23)
    - Clippings. 1972 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-5)
    - Clippings. 1973 (8 of 20 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6-13)
    - Clippings. 1973 (12 of 20 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-12)
    - Clippings. Undated, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
  - Subseries I.B. Mayoralty Years, 1960s-2000s (bulk, 1974-1977); 14.17 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged primarily in chronological order.
    The subseries of public relations files for the mayoralty years primarily includes Henry Walter's working materials as a speechwriter for Mayor Abraham Beame. The files include drafts and final versions of speeches/remarks, messages/greetings, daily press schedules, press releases, proclamations, briefing memos on appearances (e.g., other attendees, important background information, logistics), invitations for Beame to attend events and programs or other documents related to those events, executive orders, local law public hearing packages, clippings, internal memos, and other materials related to Beame's public appearances and communications. Subject matter ranges from general issues facing Beame, such as crime, politics, and business/investment climate, to specific concerns of the time, such as the city's fiscal crisis of 1975, celebration of the nation's bicentennial in 1976, the city's hosting of the Democratic National Convention in 1976, and the power outage/black-out of 1977. Files from the early months of 1977, during which time Beame ran for re-election as Mayor, include some memos and summaries related to political campaign messaging, but generally there are no extensive campaign-issued documents here. Some files include reports and other print matter and these are noted at the folder level in the container list below. Indexes to speeches/remarks given by Beame are available in the files; these tend to emphasize the group to or occasion on which Beame spoke, not the subject matter. The subseries also holds a small amount of material, such as clippings and reunion plans, relating to Beame but dating from his post-mayoralty years.
    - Beame Biographical, 1960s-1970s (Offsite-box 28, Folder 9)
      Includes three photographs of Beame's inauguration as Mayor, biographical notes from the 1970s, and some published articles about Beame.
    - Indexes, 1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
      Includes the alphabetical indexes (and some monthly chronological indexes) for Beame's remarks, statements, messages, articles, and the like during 1974. Press releases are not included in the indexes.
    - Unused Speeches, 1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
    - Personnel and Contact Phone Directories, 1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
    - Mayoral Committee Lists, 1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 4)
    - Inauguration Documents, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
      Includes program, invitation to inauguration and reception, standard portrait photograph of Beame, speech and drafts, and other documents.
    - Kenneth Kowald Correspondence, 1973 December-1974 May (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 8)
    - Proclamations. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
    - Memos. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 11)
    - Working File. 1974 January (Offsite-box 11, Folder 12)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 February (Offsite-box 11, Folder 13)
    - Press Releases. 1974 February (2 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 14-15)
    - Proclamations. 1974 February (Offsite-box 11, Folder 16)
    - Working Files. 1974 February (3 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 17-19)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 March (Offsite-box 11, Folder 20)
    - Press Releases. 1974 March (2 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 21-22)
    - Proclamations. 1974 March (Offsite-box 11, Folder 23)
    - Working Files. 1974 March (1 of 4 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 24)
    - Working Files. 1974 March (3 of 4 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 April (Offsite-box 12, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases. 1974 April (2 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Proclamations. 1974 April (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
    - Working Files. 1974 April (4 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8-11)
      Includes the booklet Giovanni da Verrazzano: The Discoveries of New York Bay by Lino S. Lipinsky, published on occasion of the inauguration of the Verrazano -Narrows Bridge on 21 November 1964.
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 May (Offsite-box 12, Folder 12)
    - Press Releases. 1974 May (Offsite-box 12, Folder 13)
    - Working Files. 1974 May (3 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 14-16)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 June (Offsite-box 12, Folder 17)
    - Press Releases. 1974 June (2 folders) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 18-19)
    - Working Files. 1974 June (4 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-4)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 July (Offsite-box 13, Folder 5)
    - Press Releases. 1974 July (Offsite-box 13, Folder 6)
    - Working Files. 1974 July (3 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7-9)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 August (Offsite-box 13, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases. 1974 August (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
    - Working Files. 1974 August (2 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12-13)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 September (Offsite-box 13, Folder 14)
    - Press Releases. 1974 September (Offsite-box 13, Folder 15)
      Includes the Department of City Planning publication Little Italy Risorgimento: Proposals for the Restoration of an Historic Community, which was the subject of press release 468-74.
    - Working Files. 1974 September (2 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 16-17)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 October (Offsite-box 13, Folder 18)
    - Press Releases. 1974 October (2 folders) (Offsite-box 13, Folder 19-20)
    - Working Files. 1974 October (4 folders) (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-4)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 November (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
    - Press Releases. 1974 November (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
    - Working Files. 1974 November (3 folders) (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7-9)
      Includes the Mayor's Policy Committee draft report Housing in New York City (Nov. 4) and final report Housing Development and Rehabilitation in New York City (Nov. 13); the program for the 40th anniversary of New York City's public housing (Nov. 20); and a marketing brochure for the Port of New York-New Jersey Authority's new passenger ship terminal on the Hudson River at mid-Manhattan (Nov. 23)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1974 December (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases. 1974 December (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11)
    - Working Files. 1974 December (4 folders) (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12-15)
      Includes a photograph of Arthur Schomburg, marketing material and fact sheets in connection with the opening of Schomberg Plaza to its first residents (Dec. 17); an image and other documents related to the presentation of a portrait of former mayor William O'Dwyer at Gracie Mansion (Dec. 20); and the Mayor's Year-End Report for 1974 (Dec. 31).
    - Working Files. Various, 1974 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 15A)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes clippings, remarks, and other documents found in other parts of the collection after processing of the Beame portion was done, and then added here.
    - Compendium of Times Editorials, Circa 1975 July (Offsite-box 14, Folder 16)
      Includes a summary of New York Times editorials concerning the impending fiscal crisis from 1974 to mid-1975, prepared about July 1975.
    - New York Times Editorial Clippings (2 folders), 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 17-18)
      Includes clippings related to the fiscal crisis, some designated as favorable or unfavorable.
    - Indexes, 1975 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
      Includes the alphabetical indexes for Beame's remarks, statements, messages, articles, and the like during 1975. Press releases are not included in the indexes.
    - Unused Material, 1975 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1975 January (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases. 1975 January (2 folders) (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - Working Files. 1975 January (4 folders) (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6-9)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1975 February (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
    - Press Releases. 1975 February (Offsite-box 15, Folder 11)
    - Working Files. 1975 February (3 folders) (Offsite-box 15, Folder 12-14)
    - Remarks, Messages, Etc. 1975 March (Offsite-box 15, Folder 15)
    - Press Releases. 1975 March (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1975 March (4 folders) (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2-5)
    - Press Releases. 1975 April (Offsite-box 16, Folder 6)
    - Working Files. 1975 April (5 folders) (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7-11)
    - Press Releases. 1975 May (Offsite-box 16, Folder 12)
    - Working Files. 1975 May (4 folders) (Offsite-box 16, Folder 13-16)
      Includes the booklet checklist for the Ash Can School exhibition at City Hall in 1975.
    - Press Releases. 1975 June (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1975 June (6 folders) (Offsite-box 17, Folder 2-7)
      Includes Beame's testimony before the Commerce, Consumer & Monetary Affairs Subcommittee of the House Committee on Government Operations (June 23) and meeting minutes of the Comptroller's Technical Debt Management Committee from February 1974-March 1975, forwarded to Beame on 2 June 1975.
    - Press Releases. 1975 July (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
    - Working Files. 1975 July (3 folders) (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9-11)
    - Press Releases. 1975 August (Offsite-box 17, Folder 12)
    - Working Files. 1975 August (2 folders) (Offsite-box 17, Folder 13-14)
    - Press Releases. 1975 September (Offsite-box 17, Folder 15)
    - Working Files. 1975 September (2 folders) (Offsite-box 17, Folder 16-17)
    - Press Releases. 1975 October (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1975 October (4 folders) (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2-5)
      The clippings include the Daily News headline "Ford to City: Drop Dead."
    - Press Releases. 1975 November (Offsite-box 18, Folder 6)
    - Working Files. 1975 November (4 folders) (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7-10)
    - Press Releases. 1975 December (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11)
    - Working Files. 1975 December (3 folders) (Offsite-box 18, Folder 12-14)
    - Indexes, 1976 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 15)
      Includes the alphabetical indexes for Beame's remarks, statements, messages, articles, and the like during 1976. Press releases are not included in the indexes.
    - Unused Speeches, 1976 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 16)
    - Press Releases. 1976 January (Offsite-box 18, Folder 17)
    - Working Files. 1976 January (2 folders) (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - Press Releases. 1976 February (Offsite-box 19, Folder 3)
    - Working Files. 1976 February (3 folders) (Offsite-box 19, Folder 4-6)
      Includes a Thomas Bartosiewicz primary election campaign pamphlet (state senator from the 18th District, Brooklyn).
    - Press Releases. 1976 March (Offsite-box 19, Folder 7)
    - Working Files. 1976 March (4 folders) (Offsite-box 19, Folder 8-11)
      Includes the booklet About American Express, a company history-oriented marketing document.
    - Press Releases. 1976 April (Offsite-box 19, Folder 12)
    - Working Files. 1976 April (4 folders) (Offsite-box 19, Folder 13-16)
      Includes the brochure checklist for the Community Environments Flag and Banner Exhibition
    - Press Releases. 1976 May (Offsite-box 19, Folder 17)
    - Working Files. 1976 May (2 of 5 folders) (Offsite-box 19, Folder 18-19)
      Includes the Bicentennial-themed program booklet for the 108th annual meeting of the Dental Society of the State of New York.
    - Working Files. 1976 May (3 of 5 folders) (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1-3)
      Includes a brochure relating the history of University Settlement (in connection with Beame's speech on the occasion of the Settlement's 90th anniversary).
    - Press Releases. 1976 June (Offsite-box 20, Folder 4)
    - Working Files. 1976 June (4 folders) (Offsite-box 20, Folder 5-9)
      Includes a selection of essays written by elementary and high school students on the subject "What I Want You to Know About New York City" for a New York Times contest; background materials from the Embassy of Spain concerning the visit of King Juan Carlos I and Queen Sophia, including two photographs of the royal family; and annual report for 1975 of the New York City Commission for the United Nations and for the Consular Corps, in connection with a 16 June 1976 speech by Beame.
    - Press Releases. 1976 July (Offsite-box 20, Folder 10)
    - Working Files. 1976 July (4 folders) (Offsite-box 20, Folder 11-14)
      Includes various materials in connection with events which Beame attended and delivered remarks: Salt Lake Mormon Tabernacle Choir information booklet and other Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints background material, including a photograph of President Spencer Wooley Kimball; lyrics to the new song "You'll Never Be Poor in New York" written by Ira Gassman, and performed at Gracie Mansion by the composer Jule Styne; Operation Sail 1976, International Naval Review and "July 4th 1976 in Old New York" brochures; Municipal Art Society award booklets for 1975 and 1976; invitation card to the Bicentennial ceremonies with Queen Elizabeth II (July 9); welcoming glossy brochure from the Citizens Committee for the Democratic National Convention to the arriving delegates (July 11); and the official commemorative program of the American Freedom Train.
    - Press Releases. 1976 August (Offsite-box 20, Folder 15)
      Includes the Department of City Planning report Schools for Communities: Expanding the Use of Our Schools (in connection with press release 295-76).
    - Working Files. 1976 August (2 folders) (Offsite-box 20, Folder 16-17)
    - Transcript of Beame Examination before the Securities & Exchange Commission in the Matter of New York City Bonds, 1976 September 1 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 18)
    - Press Releases. 1976 September (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1976 September (4 folders) (Offsite-box 21, Folder 2-5)
      Includes a compendium of remarks in connection with proclamations granting honorary citizenships, 1975-1976; the report Recommendations for a Preliminary Community District Map from the Subcommittee on Coterminality of the Mayor's Charter Implementation Committee (Sept 20); a booklet issued by Lord & Taylor in connection with its 150th anniversary (Sept 22); and a photograph of Mr. Big Apple in connection with a Committee in the Public Interest autumn campaign (Sept 30).
    - Press Releases. 1976 October (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6)
    - Special File. 1976 October (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
      Includes select Mayor Beame and Mrs. Beame speeches from October 1976; one audience, the Maritime Port Council of Greater New York & Vicinity includes both the 1976 and 1974 Beame speech.
    - Working Files. 1976 October (5 folders) (Offsite-box 21, Folder 8-12)
      Includes documents related to the dedication of the Port Richmond Water Pollution Control Plant, including the mayoral letter and list of contents placed in a box in the cornerstone to be opened in 2026 (Oct 21); recommendations of Michael I. Sovern concerning negotiations between New York and the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association (PBA) (Oct 21); brochures, including route map, for the first New York City Marathon (Oct 24); and seating list, program and other documents related to the New York Press Club's Byline Ball at which Beame was roasted (Oct 24).
    - Press Releases. 1976 November (Offsite-box 21, Folder 13)
    - Report to the Securities & Exchange Commission, 1976 November 23 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 14)
      Includes the report of the Special Counsel to New York City concerning its investigation of transactions in city securities. Also includes a memo of December 2, 1974, stating reasons for the frequency of New York's short term borrowings and higher total borrowings.
    - Working Files. 1976 November (3 folders) (Offsite-box 21, Folder 15-17)
    - Press Releases. 1976 December (Offsite-box 21, Folder 18)
    - Working Files. 1976 December (2 of 3 folders) (Offsite-box 21, Folder 19-20)
      Includes a photograph of the New York Cultural Center (Gallery of Modern Art) and other buildings at Columbus Circle in connection with its purchase and donation to the city by Gulf & Western (Dec 8); documents, including an exterior photograph, related to the opening of the Museum of Holography at 11 Mercer Street (Dec 8); and the Department of Investigation's report of the management audit of the Department of Purchase (Dec 10).
    - Working Files. 1976 December (1 of 3 folders) (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1)
    - Indexes, 1977 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 2)
    - Press Releases. 1977 January (Offsite-box 22, Folder 3)
    - Working Files. 1977 January (2 folders) (Offsite-box 22, Folder 4-5)
    - Press Releases. 1977 February (Offsite-box 22, Folder 6)
    - Working Files. 1977 February (3 folders) (Offsite-box 22, Folder 7-9)
    - Press Releases. 1977 March (Offsite-box 22, Folder 10)
    - Working Files. 1977 March (4 folders) (Offsite-box 22, Folder 11-14)
      Includes the original mayoral proclamation of Kazoo Day (March 18).
    - Press Releases. 1977 April (Offsite-box 22, Folder 15)
    - Working Files. 1977 April (3 folders) (Offsite-box 22, Folder 16-18)
      Includes an October 1961 brochure issued by the Municipal Art Society of New York, The City Hall of the City of New York.
    - Press Releases. 1977 May (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1)
    - Working Files. 1977 May (8 folders) (Offsite-box 23, Folder 2-9)
      Includes Beame's re-election campaign announcement and documents concerning story lines and responses to questions about the 1975 fiscal crisis in relation to the campaign. Includes documents related to the Americana '77 Street Fair, including street maps showing location and type of exhibits.
    - Press Releases. 1977 June (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
      Includes the Preliminary Report on Flushing Airport prepared by Transportation Administrator Alexander J. Mautner (press release 247-77).
    - Working Files. 1977 June (6 folders) (Offsite-box 23, Folder 11-16)
      Includes the Official Statement for the issuance by New York City of $381,750,000 of General Obligation Serial Bonds (June 16).
    - Press Releases. 1977 July (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1)
      Includes the Preliminary Findings: Blackout Commercial Damage Survey prepared by the Department of City Planning (press release 339-77).
    - Working Files. 1977 July (3 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 2-4)
      Includes the transcript of the interview of mayoral candidate Edward I. Koch on the program "New York Report" on WOR-TV Channel 9 Public Affairs (July 25); and the New Yorker with Ken Auletta's article "More for Less" (August 1), the letter from the New Yorker informing Beame of the impending article, and Beame's rebuttal.
    - Press Releases. 1977 August (2 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5-6)
      Includes the booklet Trees for New York City prepared by the Department of City Planning, with enclosed oversize reference sheet of tree information (press release 391-77).
    - Working Files. 1977 August (4 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 7-10)
      Includes the internal report of New York City "Weekly Indicators" for August 1-14, prepared by the Research Section of the Economic Development Administration; photocopy of the interview report for David Berkowitz ("Son of Sam") prepared by the Pretrial Services Agency (Aug. 11) (Includes only basic identifying information); and the report from accountants Peat, Marwick, Mitchell in response to questions posed by the Emergency Financial Control Board (Aug. 11).
    - Press Releases. 1977 September (Offsite-box 24, Folder 11)
    - Working Files. 1977 September (3 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 12-14)
    - Press Releases. 1977 October (Offsite-box 24, Folder 15)
    - Working Files. 1977 October (2 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 16-17)